原视频名：How Europe Designed and Evolved The Ariane Rocket Over Last 4 Decades
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/DFbzvbkoEYs
原视频发布日期：20191227
字幕翻译/压制：旋火，校对：CNplee
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
It's a day past Christmas and I missed a very important birthday,
这是一个圣诞节之后的一天 而我错过了一个非常重要的生日
the 40th anniversary of the first launch of the Ariane rocket.
那就是阿丽亚娜火箭首飞40周年
Yes back on ChristmasEve 1979 Europe launched the Ariane 1
是的 早在1979年圣诞节前夕 欧洲就发射了阿丽亚娜1号火箭
but Europe's space launch ambitions started decades earlier.
但欧洲航天发射的雄心早在几十年前就开始了
Much more politics was involved since it was an international organization.
由于这是一个国际组织 所以涉及的政治因素更多
The Europa launcher was originally planned in 1962
欧罗巴号运载火箭最初计划于1962年发射
and it was led by the UK with France and Germany as main collaborators.
并由英国牵头 而法国和德国为主要合作者
The UK had developed a missile called the Blue Streak but it had never deployed it.
英国曾研制出一种名为蓝纹的导弹 但从未部署过
They had proposed this as the first stage for the Europa rocket
他们曾建议将其作为欧罗巴火箭的一级
with the French building the second stage and Germany building the third stage.
法国负责二级的制造 德国负责三级的制造
This made integration problematic.
这使得整合出现了问题
Ultimately it didn't fly particularly well
最终 它并没有飞得特别好
and Britain pulled out the project in 1968 to develop their own Black Arrow.
而英国在1968年退出了这个项目 发展自己的黑箭火箭
Germany pulled out in 1972 and the program officially stopped in 1973.
德国在1972年退出 该项目在1973年正式停止
So in the meantime the British black arrow project successfully launched hardware into orbit
所以在这期间 英国的黑箭项目成功地将设备发射到了轨道上
and then promptly stopped doing anything.
然后马上就不干了
The French developed the Diamant rocket which was able to launch about a dozen times with nine successes.
法国人研制的钻石火箭 发了十几次 其中九次成功
But it was only able to put about 160 kilograms into low earth orbit.
但它只能把160公斤左右的重量送入近地轨道
And so Ariane started out as a project called L3S
所以阿丽亚娜一开始的项目叫L3S
with the goal of designing a rocket that would be able to launch 800 kilograms to geostationary orbit
目标是设计一种能够将800公斤的载荷发射到地球静止轨道(GEO)的火箭
and this is significant
而这是相当可以的
because Ariane I believe is the only rocket that has been designed from the start
因为我相信阿丽亚娜是唯一的 从一开始就这样设计的火箭
with the intention of launching payloads to geostationary orbit rather than low earth orbit.
其设计目的就是将有效载荷发射到地球静止轨道而不是近地轨道
The name Ariane comes from Greek mythology.
阿丽亚娜这个名字来自希腊神话
In english we know her as Ariadne.
在英语中 我们知道她是阿里阿德涅
She gave Theseus the thread
她给了忒修斯一条线
that he used to find his way out of the labyrinth after defeating the minotaur.
在打败牛头人后 他用它找到了走出迷宫的方法
In French she was known as Ariane.
在法国 她被称为阿丽亚娜
Ariane was very much led by the French with 60 percent of the funding coming from France.
阿丽亚娜是由法国人牵头的 60%的资金来自法国
20 percent of the funding came from Germany
20%的资金来自德国
and most of the other European nations contributed a few percent to the project.
而大多数其他欧洲国家为该项目贡献了百分之几的资金
The design of the Ariane would borrow from work already done on the Europa booster.
阿丽亚娜的设计将使用欧罗巴助推器上已经完成的工作
After Britain left they sought a replacement first stage booster
在英国离开后 他们在寻求一级助推器的替代品
and they came up with a stage that had four Viking engines
于是 他们做出了一个有四台维京发动机的一级
using steel tanks for the hypergolic propellants of nitrogen tetroxide and UDMH.
使用装有四氧化二氮和偏二甲肼这样的自燃推进剂的钢制储罐
This would be the first stage of the Ariane.
这将是阿丽亚娜的第一级
With the propellant tanks full the first stage had a mass of about 160 tons.
在推进剂储罐装满后 一级的质量约为160吨
It's also notable that in addition to the oxidizer and the fuel tanks
另外值得注意的是 除了氧化剂和燃料箱外
there was a smaller toroidal shaped water tank at the bottom.
在底部有一个较小的环形水箱
So this is because of the way the Viking engine operates.
那么这是因为维京发动机的运作方式
As you probably know
你可能知道
many high performance rocket engines they have a gas generator that powers the turbo pumps
许多高性能的火箭发动机会有一个气体发生器 为涡轮泵提供动力
that is they burn some fuel and the oxidizer and use the exhaust gas to power turbines.
即它们燃烧一些燃料和氧化剂 并使用废气驱动涡轮机
To keep the temperature down
为了降低温度
the fuel and the oxidizer are mixed in ratios that don't result in complete combustion.
燃料和氧化剂的混合比例会导致不完全燃烧
Usually it's a fuel rich mixture
通常情况下 这会是富燃的混合方式
and in the case of SpaceX's Merlin
而在SpaceX的梅林发动机的情况下
you can actually see the fuel rich exhaust black exhaust coming out of the side.
你实际上可以看到富燃的黑色排气从侧面出来
The Viking instead uses mixes at a stoichiometric ratio
维京发动机使用的混合比是理想的
and it then cools that exhaust down using water.
然后它使用水将该废气冷却下来
Not only does this make the exhaust gases cool enough to be used with the turbine
这不仅使废气冷却到足以给涡轮机使用的程度
they also take some of those high pressure exhaust gases and use those to repressurize propellant tanks.
他们还能从高压废气中提取一些气体 用来重新增压推进剂罐
And you couldn't do that if it was you know say fuel rich exhaust
如果是富燃的废气 你就无法做到这一点
because putting fuel-rich hypergolic exhaust into a hypergolic oxidizer
因为将富燃的自燃燃料废气排入自燃氧化剂中
would result in combustion inside the tank which is a really bad idea.
会导致储罐内部发生燃烧 这会是一个非常糟糕的想法
The four engines are mounted at the outer edge of the thrust structure on the bottom of the rocket
四台发动机安装在火箭底部推力结构的外缘
and they all have single engine gimbals which are slightly easier than having multi-axis gimbals
而且发动机都能单向摆动 这比多向摆动要容易一些
but by moving the engines in pairs they are able to provide full three-axis control of the launch vehicle.
但通过成对摆动发动机 他们能够对运载火箭进行完全的三轴控制
The second stage also used the Viking engine
二级也使用了维京发动机
but there was only one of them with a two-axis gimbal to provide full yaw and pitch control.
但只有一台 这台带有两轴矢量摆动 以提供完全的偏航和俯仰控制
The gas generator exhaust was diverted through auxiliary nozzles to provide roll control.
燃气发生器的废气通过辅助喷嘴引流 以提供滚转控制
When fully loaded with propellant, the second stage massed about 40 tons
当满载推进剂时 二级的质量约为40吨
and unlike the first stage its structure and tankage were aluminium rather than steel.
与一级不同的是 它的结构和储罐是铝制的而不是钢
The third stage was a high energy hydrogen oxygen stage powered by an HM7 engine.
三级是由HM7发动机驱动的高能氢氧级
This is a simple gas generator hydrogen oxygen engine.
这是一台简单的气体发生器(循环)氢氧发动机
This stage would have over eight tons of propellant.
这级将有超过8吨的推进剂
And would boost the payload up into geostationary transfer orbit.
并会将有效载荷送到地球静止转移轨道(GTO)上
There was a fourth optional stage for payloads that went to GEO.
还有四级可选 用于将有效载荷(直接)送入地球同步轨道(Scott 口胡GTO)
This was the Mage solid rocket motor.
这是Mage固体火箭发动机
It was just an apogee kick motor to put the payload into a circular orbit.
这只是一个在远地点工作的发动机 能将有效载荷送入圆形轨道
The first full-up integrated test of the Ariane 1 was going to be on December 15 1979.
阿丽亚娜1号的第一次全面综合试验 将于1979年12月15日进行
It was going to carry a payload of test instruments called CAT-1.
它将携带被称为CAT-1的测试仪器的有效载荷
They were stacked and on December 15th they counted down.
在12月15日 火箭被堆叠起来 并进行倒计时
The engines ignited and 10 seconds later the computer shut down the engines.
发动机点火 10秒钟后 电脑关闭了发动机
Because it wasn't sure the rocket was going to be able to fly.
因为它不确定火箭是否能飞起来
It never left the pad and the engineers spent the next week
它一直没有离开过发射台 而工程师们在接下来的一周里
cleaning the rocket preparing it tracing the problem
清洗火箭 准备火箭 追查问题
and then on December 23rd they were ready to launch again and the weather wasn't cooperative
然后在12月23日 他们准备再次发射 但天气并不配合
but on December 24th the first Ariane one took off
但在12月24日 第一枚阿丽亚娜1号火箭起飞了
and successfully placed the satellite into its target orbit.
并成功地将卫星送入其目标轨道
The second launch would unfortunately be destroyed by pogo oscillations.
遗憾的是 第二次发射将因纵向藕合振动而被摧毁
The third launch was the first one to geostationary orbit using the Mage apogee booster.
第三次发射会使用Mage远地点火箭 并首次进入地球静止轨道
In total there would be 11 launches of this launch vehicle with two of them being failures.
这种运载火箭总共进行了11次发射 其中两次失败
Orobably its most famous payload was the Giotto spacecraft
其最著名的有效载荷是乔托号探测器
which made the closest approach to Halley's comet of any spacecraft
它是所有航天器中最接近哈雷彗星的航天器
and it flew right up until 1986 by which time it had been replaced by the Ariane 3.
而阿丽亚娜1号一直飞到1986年才被阿丽亚娜3号取代
What happened to the Ariane 2?
那么阿丽亚娜2号后来怎么了？
Well actually the Ariane 2 flew.
其实阿丽亚娜2号曾经飞过
It just started flying later than the Ariane 3.
只是比阿丽亚娜3号晚了一些
So Ariane 2 and 3 were developed in parallel as improved versions of the Ariane 1.
那么阿丽亚娜2号和3号是作为阿丽亚娜1号的改进版同时开发的
These changes were designed to make it more appealing to the commercial launch market.
这些变化的目的是为了让它对商业发射市场更有吸引力
In the late 1970s when they were designing this
在20世纪70年代末 当他们在设计阿丽亚娜火箭的时候
the rides to geostationary orbit were the Delta that could put about 1200 kilograms into GTO
能发射到GEO的火箭是德尔塔火箭 可以把大约1200公斤的重量送入GTO
and the Atlas-Centaur who was which was roughly comparable to the Ariane 1.
而宇宙神-半人马座火箭 与阿丽亚娜1号(的运力)大致相当
The Ariane 1 found itself more expensive than the Delta but a lot cheaper than the Atlas-Centaur
而阿丽亚娜1号比德尔塔贵 但比宇宙神-半人马便宜很多
but most of the market were looking for payloads that could fly on the Delta
但市场上大多数人都在寻找可以在德尔塔上飞行的有效载荷
so the plan was to extend the payload capability of the Ariane
那么计划是扩大阿丽亚娜的有效载荷运力
and put two spacecraft on a single launch vehicle.
并能进行一箭双星任务的发射
So they needed to get more performance from their existing vehicle.
所以他们需要从现有的运载火箭上获得更多的性能
What did they do?
那他们做了什么呢？
The first thing they did was they changed the fuel.
他们做的第一件事就是改变燃料
The Ariane 1 used pure UDMH.
阿丽亚娜1号使用的是纯偏二甲肼
They started adding about 25 percent hydrazine.
(于是)他们开始添加25%的肼
The hydrazine is less stable but it provides better specific impulse
肼的稳定性较差 但能提供更好的比冲
and so they got about an extra 10 percent chamber pressure out of this.
所以燃烧室增加了10%的压力
They added two solid propellant boosters which each had a thrust of about 60 tons.
他们加装了两个固体推进剂助推器 每个助推器的推力约为60吨
Those would be on the Ariane 3.
这些将被安装在阿丽亚娜3号上
The Ariane 2 would not need these.
阿丽亚娜2号不需要这些助推器
And the third stage had the tank stretched so that it could carry 10 tons of propellant.
而三级的储箱被拉长了 所以它可以携带10吨的推进剂
With all these changes the Ariane 3 was able to launch two 1200 kilogram satellites in a single launch.
通过这些改变 阿丽亚娜3号能够在一次发射中发射两颗1200公斤的卫星
Inside the payload fairing there would be a structure called the Sylda
在有效载荷整流罩内会有一个叫做Sylda的结构
which was like a carbon fiber shell that would support the top satellite and enclose the lower satellite.
它差不多是一个碳纤维外壳 会支撑顶部的卫星并包围下部的卫星
By putting two payloads on a single launch
通过一次发射两个有效载荷
that allowed them to significantly cut their costs for all the ground operations
能使他们大幅削减所有地面操作的成本
since they're only launching one rocket they're getting two payloads and two customers.
因为只发射一枚火箭就搭载了两个客户的两个有效载荷
So Arianespace was able to make big moves in the commercial market
所以阿丽亚娜空间能够在商业市场上有大的动作
but the market didn't stay still and bigger and better capabilities were desired.
但市场并没有停滞不前 而人们希望有更大更好的性能
Ariane 2 only flew 6 times and Ariane 3 only flew 11 times
阿丽亚娜2号只飞了6次 而阿丽亚娜3号只飞了11次
and Ariane 4 would replace both of them.
而阿丽亚娜4号将取代这两枚运载火箭
Ariane 4's goal was to launch 4300 kilograms worth of satellites.
阿丽亚娜4号的目标是发射总重4300公斤的有效载荷
It was still able to launch two of them.
它仍能够发射两颗卫星
The way it did this was the first stage tankage was increased in size
增加运力的方法是一级储箱被拉长了
so that was able to carry about 230 tons of propellant.
这样就能携带约230吨的推进剂
The water tank was moved up the rocket into the intertank region between the oxidizer and propellant tank.
而火箭上的水箱上移到了氧化剂储箱和燃料储箱之间的箱间段
The second and third stages were identical
二级和三级和之前是相同的
but what Ariane 4 added was up to four external boosters.
但阿丽亚娜4号可以捆绑多达四个外部助推器
And these could either be solid propellant or liquid propellant depending upon mission requirements.
根据任务要求 这些助推器可以是固体推进剂的 也可以是液体推进剂的
The bare core with no boosters was rated to put 2100 kilograms into geostationary transfer orbit.
没有助推器的光杆火箭的地球静止转移轨道运力是2100公斤
If it had four solid rocket motors that would be raised to about 3400 kilograms
如果它有四个固体火箭发动机 就会提高到3400公斤左右
and if it had four liquid boosters that would do 4 700 kilograms into geostationary transfer orbit.
如果使用四个液体助推器 就可以将4700公斤的重量送入地球静止转移轨道
This was the most popular variant.
这是最受欢迎的种类
As of right now the Ariane 4 is the most popular of the Ariane 5 rockets
目前阿丽亚娜4号是5种阿丽亚娜火箭中最受欢迎的型号
having launched 116 times with only three failures.
发射了116次 只有三次失败
It continued launching concurrently with the much heavier Ariane 5
它继续与更重的阿丽亚娜5号同时发射
until it was eventually retired and the medium launches then moved over to the Soyuz launch vehicle.
直到它最终退役 而中型运载火箭的发射转移到联盟运载火箭上
But as of right now the Ariane 5 is currently active and it is catching up with the Ariane 4.
但是就目前来说 阿丽亚娜5号正在服役 它正在追赶阿丽亚娜4号
It has 106 launches. 101 of those have been successful.
它已经发射了106次 其中有101次是成功的
The Ariane 5 is a huge break in the design philosophy compared to the Ariane 4.
与阿丽亚娜4号相比 阿丽亚娜5号在设计理念上有很大的突破
The Ariane 5 design requirements had it launching a pair of three-ton satellites into geostationary transfer orbit
阿丽亚娜5号的设计要求是将一对3吨重的卫星发射到地球静止转移轨道
but it also specified the ability to launch an 18-ton payload into a low earth orbit
但也包括将18吨重的有效载荷发射到低地球轨道的能力
and this was for the Hermes space plane
这是为赫尔墨斯航天飞机准备的
which while the Ariane 5 was built with this in mind the space plane never made it to flight.
虽然阿丽亚娜5号在建造的时候就考虑到了这一点 但航天飞机却没有飞起来
Some people have suggested that
有些人认为
the space plane requirements meant the Ariane 5 was way too big for its purpose.
对于航天飞机的要求 阿丽亚娜5号(的运力)实在是太大了
But the truth is Ariane had always been launching pairs of satellites
但事实上 阿丽亚娜5号一直在进行双星任务
so this just continued that trend
所以 这只是在持续那个趋势
and indeed this large payload requirement has meant that
事实上 这一庞大的有效载荷要求意味着
they have remained the most popular launch vehicle for geostationary spacecraft.
它们一直是地球静止轨道航天器最受欢迎的运载火箭
The base design has two very large solid rocket motors
基础设计有两个非常大的固体火箭发动机
each massing about 300 tons.
每个质量约300吨
And a hydrogen oxygen core that fully fueled is about 170 tons.
而完全加满燃料的氢氧芯级约为170吨
The engine on the core is the Vulcan which is a gas generator hydrogen oxygen engine.
芯级上的发动机是火神发动机 是气体发生器(循环)的氢氧发动机
There is a second stage which is hypergolic.
二级使用的是自燃推进剂
It's powered by the Aestus engine.
它由Aestus发动机提供动力
And it uses monomethylhydrazine and nitrogen tetroxide
推进剂使用的是单甲基肼和四氧化二氮
and the main distinction here over the previous Viking is that
和以前的维京发动机相比 这里的主要区别是
this engine on this upper stage is restartable so it can be fired multiple times.
这个上面级发动机是可以重新启动的 所以可以多次点火
The original Ariane was the G variant.
最初的阿丽亚娜5号是G型的
They upgraded it a bit to create the G plus
他们对它进行了一些升级 也就是G+型
and in 2005 they debuted an Ariane 5 with a cryogenic upper stage
并在2005年首次推出了带有低温上面级的阿丽亚娜5号
using the same HM7B engine that was used to propel the upper stages for the previous generation Arianes.
使用与上一代阿丽亚娜4号上面级所使用发动机相同的HM7B发动机
With this upper stage it was now able to put a 10.8 tonnes into geostationary transfer orbit.
有了这个上面级 它现在能够把一个10.8吨的东西送入地球静止转移轨道
That's the record they set in 2017.
这是他们在2017年创造的记录
It still has plenty of launches lined up.
阿丽亚娜5号还有很多发射任务在排队
Notably it's going to launch the James Webb Space Telescope
值得注意的是 它将发射詹姆斯-韦伯太空望远镜
and the Jupiter Icy Moons Explorer in coming years.
和未来几年的木星冰月探测器(JUICE)
阿6已经鸽子到2022年了
But at the same time Ariane 6 is in development and could be is launching as soon as next year.
但与此同时 阿丽亚娜6号正在研制中 最快可能在明年发射
At one point Ariane 6 was proposed to be almost all solid rocket motors with cryogenic upper stages.
阿丽亚娜6号曾一度被提议几乎完全采用固体火箭发动机和低温上面级
But they dialed that back
但他们又将其调了回来
and now it's much closer to an Ariane 5 with shorter solid rocket motors
而现在它更接近于一个有着更短的固体火箭发动机的阿丽亚娜5号
and a larger upper stage using the Vinci engine which is a hydrolox engine.
以及使用芬奇氢氧发动机的更大的上面级
So that's what the future holds for the Ariane rocket family.
所以这就是阿丽亚娜火箭家族的未来
Still going strong after 40 years.
40年后仍在茁壮成长
Happy birthday.
祝你生日快乐
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全